Leah: So, what is a database?
A database is an ‘organised structured
collection of data’ which can be easily managed.
The data is normally organised in tables which
contain rows, columns, and indexes that make it
easier to search and find relevant information.
There are many different types of databases
but before we go into these first let’s first
start by looking at ‘unstructured data’.
Chris: Unstructured data is not organised
and can be stored in a number of ways.
For example, a letter has ‘structure’ in
the way it is arranged on the page [e.g.
Date, address, salutation, heading, letter
content, signature etc], but the actual ‘data’
in the letter would be ‘unstructured’ so would
not be able to be manipulated in any way.
Leah: However, if that same letter was used as a template
for a mail-merge, then the data that would be used to
generate the output letters, would in fact be ‘structured
data’ as the data would be stored in a structured way
as in a table such names and addresses of recipients.
Here are some items that would be
classified as unstructured data:
• Chris: Emails – these could be business or personal
• Document files such as letters, reports, presentations
• Websites – most web content is regarded as unprocessed
and unstructured, and on some websites the unstructured
data could be used for SEO [Search Engine Optimisation].
• Media such as images, video, or audio
• Mobile data such as text messages
• Communication such as team chats
• Social media – although technically a website this
is a little different as most social media websites
are considered both unstructured and structured data.
There are some elements which is unstructured data
such as a user post, but there are other elements which
would be stored as structured data such as user details.
Leah: It is important to recognise the distinction
between ‘structured’ and ‘structured data’ as many of the
these ‘items’ we have mentioned are in fact ‘structured’
like a letter, but their data is ‘unstructured’.
Nearly all types of Databases
contain data that is ‘structured’.
By structured we mean data that can be organised,
analysed, indexed, searched, and easy to understand.
Chris: Here is a table of data that is ‘unstructured’
Now if we were to ‘structure’ this data it would
look like this and be much easier to understand.
There are many different types of databases used today
and most are enclosed within a database management
system [DBMS] within which the data is stored in tables
and can be manipulated or analysed using queries.
Leah: A database uses structured
query language [SQL] to do this.
SQL is often used by businesses to run statistical reports,
so, for example a college could generate a report from their
‘learning database’ using a query to ask, ‘how many learners
are studying a specific course in a specific month’.
Databases make it easy to store information that is quick
and easy to search for, due to their index capabilities,
and most websites use databases to store data.
A lot of websites use MySQL which is an
‘open-source’ Relational database system.
Chris: Nonrelational databases [NoSQL] have become
more popular in recent years as they offer a more
flexible, scalable alternative to the traditional
SQL ‘Relational database management system’ [RDBMS].
RDBMS work better for data that is more simple and static.
NoSQL databases allow the use of ‘unstructured data’
whereas RDBMS are table based and therefore structured.
So, for example, in the case of websites and
social media, the unstructured data could
be used for SEO or marketing campaigns.
Leah: Cloud databases are stored on the
‘Cloud’ which could be private, public or a
hybrid cloud platform and there are two types
– ‘traditional’ or ‘Database as a service’ [DBaaS].
Open source databases can be SQL or NoSQL
and as we have said one of the most well
used is ‘MySQL’ which is an ‘RDBMS’.
Other common database types include
‘Object-oriented’, ‘Distributed’, ‘Graph’,
‘OLTP databases’ and ‘Data warehouse’.
Less common types which are more specific to their
areas of work and specialism include ‘Multi-model’,
‘Document/JSON’, and ‘Self-driving databases’.
Chris: Check out our website section
on this page to find out more.